So 24 years ago,
منذ 24 سنة،
I was brought to The New Yorker
جئت إلى جريدة (ذا نيويوركر)
as art editor
بصفتي محررة فنية
to rejuvenate
لتجديد
what had by then become a somewhat staid institution
ما أصبح بعد ذلك مؤسسة رزينة نوعًا ما
and to bring in new artists
ولإحضار فنانين جدد
and to try to bring the magazine from its ivory tower
ولمحاولة إخراج المجلة من عزلتها
into engaging with its time.
ومعاصرة زمنها.
And it was just the right thing for me to do
وكان ذلك الشيء الصحيح الذي أقوم به
because I've always been captivated by how an image can --
لأنني كنت دائمًا مفتونة بقدرة صورة ما
a simple drawing --
أو رسمة بسيطة --
can cut through the torrent of images that we see every single day.
على شق طريقها عبر كثير من الصور التي نراها يوميًَا
How it can capture a moment,
كيف يمكنها أن تأسر لحظة،
how it can crystallize a social trend or a complex event
وكيف يمكنها أن تبلور حالة اجتماعية أو حدثًا معقدًا
in a way that a lot of words wouldn't be able to do --
بطريقة تعجز عن فعلها الكثير من الكلمات --
and reduce it to its essence and turn it into a cartoon.
وتستخلص جوهرها وتحوله إلى صورة متحركة.
So I went to the library
إذًا، ذهبت إلى المكتبة
and I looked at the first cover drawn by Rea Irvin in 1925 --
ونظرت إلى أول غلاف رسمَته (ريا إيفرن) سنة 1925
a dandy looking at a butterfly through his monocle,
شخصية رجل من الطراز الأول ينظر إلى فراشة صغيرة عبر منظاره،
and we call it Eustace Tilley.
أطلق عليها اسم (يوستاس تيلي)
And I realized that as the magazine had become known
و أدركت أنه مع شهرة المجلة المكتسبة
for its in-depth research and long reports,
لأبحاثها العميقة ومقالاتها الطويلة،
some of the humor had gotten lost along the way,
ضاعت بعض الفكاهات مع الوقت،
because now often Eustace Tilley was seen as a haughty dandy,
لأن (يوستاس تيلي) غالبًا ما يُرى أنه شخصية تاريخية متعجرفة
but in fact, in 1925,
لكن في الواقع، أنه في عام 1925،
when Rea Irvin first drew this image,
عندما رسم ريا إيفرن هذه الرسمة لأول مرة،
he did it as part of a humor magazine
رسمها كجزء من مجلة فكاهية
to amuse the youth of the era,
ليضحك بها شباب تلك الحقبة،
which was the flappers of the roaring twenties.
الذي اشتهر بالمراهقات الصاخبات (راجع Flappers في ويكيبيديا)
And in the library,
وفي المكتبة،
I found the images that really captured the zeitgeist
وجدت هذه الصور التي اتسمت بروح ذلك العصر
of the Great Depression.
أيام الكساد الكبير (أزمة اقتصادية في 1929)
And it showed us not just how people dressed
ولم تظهر لنا ماذا يلبس الناس فحسب،
or what their cars looked like,
أو كيف بدت سياراتهم،
but also what made them laugh,
بل ما كان يضحكهم كذلك،
what their prejudices were.
وإلى ماذا كانوا يتعصبون.
And you really got a sense
وكنت تشعر بشكل حقيقي
of what it felt like to be alive in the '30s.
كيف لو كنت موجودًا أيام الثلاثينيات.
So I called on contemporary artists,
لذا دعوت فنانين معاصرين،
such as Adrian Tomine here.
كـ (أدريان توماين) هنا.
I often call on narrative artists --
وكثيرًا ما أدعو فناني القصص والسرد --
cartoonists, children's book authors --
راسمي الكرتون وكتّاب كتب الأطفال --
and I give them themes such as,
وأعطيهم مواضيعًا تصف
you know, what it's like to be in the subway,
أحوالنا ونحن في المترو، كمثال
or Valentine's Day,
أو عيد الحب،
and they send me sketches.
ويرسلون لي رسومًا تصويرية.
And once the sketches are approved by the editor,
وحالما يقوم المحرر بقبولها،
David Remnick,
(دايفد ريمنيك)،
it's a go.
فهذا يعني الموافقة عليها.
And I love the way
وأحببت كيف أن
those images are actually not telling you what to think.
هذه الصور لا تخبرك بالفكرة مباشرة
But they do make you think,
بل تجعلك تفكر،
because the artist is actually --
لأن الفنان في الحقيقة --
it's almost a puzzle;
لغز تقريبًا؛
the artist is drawing the dots,
يرسم الفنان النقاط،
and you, the reader, have to complete the picture.
وعليك أيها القارئ أن تكمل الصورة.
So to get this image on the left by Anita Kunz,
لذا لفهم الصورة على اليسار والتي رستمها (أنيتا كونز)،
or the one on right by Tomer Hanuka,
أو التي على اليمين والتي رسمها (تومير هانوكا)،
you have to play spot the differences.
عليك أن تلعب لعبة (البحث عن الفروق)
And it is something that ...
وهو أمر
It's really exciting to see
ممتع أن ترى
how the engagement with the reader ...
كيف أن ارتباط القراء ..
how those images really capture --
كيف أن هذه الصور تلتقط
play with the stereotypes.
أو تُظهر الصور النمطية لديهم.
But when you get it,
لكن حينما تُفهم الفكرة،
it rearranges the stereotypes that are in your head.
فإنها تعيد ترتيب الصور النمطية في رؤوس القراء.
But the images don't just have to show people,
لكن الصور لا تقتصر على إظهار أناس فقط
sometimes it can be a feeling.
بل قد تُظهر مشاعر أحيانًا.
Right after September 11,
بعد أحادث 11 سبتمبر مباشرة،
I was at a point,
كنت في وضعٍ،
like everybody else,
مثل أي شخص آخر حينها،
where I really didn't know how to deal with what we were going through,
لا أعرف كيف أتعامل مع ما كنًا سنخوضه
and I felt that no image could capture this moment,
و شعرت أنه لا يوجد صورة من الممكن أن تصف تلك اللحظة،
and I wanted to just do a black cover,
أردت فقط أن أضع غلافًا أسود.
like no cover.
كأنه لا غلاف.
And I talked to my husband, cartoonist Art Spiegelman,
وتحدثت مع زوجي الرسام الكاريكتوري (سبيجلمان)
and mentioned to him that I was going to propose that,
وذكرت له ما كنت أنوي فعله
and he said, "Oh, if you're going to do a black cover,
وقال: "إذا كنت ستقومي بعمل غلاف أسود،
then why don't you do the silhouette of the Twin Towers,
فلماذا لا تقومين بعمل صورة ظلية للبرجين،
black on black?"
سواد فوق سواد؟"
And I sat down to draw this,
وجلست لرسم لذلك،
and as soon as I saw it,
وبمجرد أن رأيته،
a shiver ran down my spine
ارتعشت عظامي من الخوف
and I realized
و تبيّن لي
that in this refusal to make an image,
كيف أن في هذا الرفض لصنع صورة،
we had found a way to capture loss
وجدنا طريقًا لإظهار فقدنا
and mourning
وحدادنا
and absence.
والغياب الذي نشعر به.
And it's been a profound thing that I learned in the process --
وكان شيئًا عميقًا تعلمته من هذه التجربة
that sometimes some of the images that say the most
أنه في بعض الأحيان أن بعض الصور تقول أكثر
do it with the most spare means.
مما تفعله معظم وسائل التعبير الأخرى.
And a simple image can speak volumes.
و أن صورة بسيطة قد تغني عن مجلدت.
So this is the image that we published by Bob Staake
وهذه الصورة التي صنعها (بوب ستاك)
right after the election of Barack Obama,
ونُشرت مباشرة بعد انتخاب باراك أوباما،
and captured a historic moment.
و وثّقت لحظة تاريخية.
But we can't really plan for this,
لكننا لا نستطيع حقًا أن نخطط لمثل هذا،
because in order to do this,
لأنه من أجل فعل ذلك،
we have to let the artist experience the emotions that we all feel
يجب علينا أن ندع الرسام يشعر بما نشعر به جميعنا
when that is happening.
خلال حدوث الحدث
So back in November 2016,
في نوفمبر 2016
during the election last year,
وخلال الانتخابات
the only image that we could publish was this,
الصورة الوحيدة التي استطعنا نشرها كانت هذه
which was on the stand on the week that everybody voted.
وقد كانت هناك أمام كل شخص انتخب في ذلك الاسبوع
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Because we knew somebody would feel this --
لأننا كنا نعلم أن بعض الأشخاص سيشعرون بذلك
when the result of the election was announced.
عندما أُعلنت نتائج الانتخابات
And when we found out the result,
وعندما عرفنا النتيجة
we really were at a loss,
شعرنا بالفعل بالخسارة
and this is the image that was sent by Bob Staake again,
وهذه الصورة التي أُرسلت من قبل (بوب ستاك) مرة أخرى
and that really hit a chord.
وكانت بالفعل في مكانها
And again,
ومرة أخرى،
we can't really figure out what's going to come next,
لم نستطع معرفة ماذا سيحدث لاحقًا
but here it felt like we didn't know how to move forward,
لكن هنا كنا نشعر بأننا لم نعرف كيف نتقدم
but we did move forward,
لكننا استطعنا التقدم،
and this is the image that we published after Donald Trump's election
وكانت هذه الصورة التي نُشرت مباشرة بعد انتخاب (ترمب)
and at the time of the Women's March
في يوم المرأة العالمي
all over the US.
في كل أنحاء أمريكا.
So over those 24 years,
إذن في خلال هذه الـ 24 سنة
I have seen over 1,000 images come to life week after week,
شاهدت أكثر من 1000 صورة تُنشر كل أسبوع
and I'm often asked which one is my favorite,
وكثيرًا ما أُسْأَلَ عن المفضلة لدي،
but I can't pick one
ولكني لا أستطيع اختيار واحدة
because what I'm most proud of is how different every image is,
لأن ما أفخر به حقًا هو كيف أن كل صورة تختلف
one from the other.
عن الأخرى
And that's due to the talent and the diversity
والذي يعود للمواهب والتنوع
of all of the artists that contribute.
الذي يتمتع به الرسامين المشاركين.
And now, well,
والآن،
now, we're owned by Russia,
والآن، نحن نعتبر من أملاك روسيا
so --
إذن --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
In a rendering by Barry Blitt here,
وفي إعادة الرسم هنا من قبل (باري بيلت)
Eustace has become Eustace Vladimirovich Tilley.
أصبح (يوستاس) (يوستاس فلاديميروفيتش تيلي)
And the butterfly is none other than a flabbergasted Donald Trump
والفراشة ليست سوى دونالد ترامب حائر
flapping his wings,
ترفرف أجنحته
trying to figure out how to control the butterfly effect,
محاولًا معرفة كيفية التحكم في تأثير الفراشة
and the famed logo that was drawn by Rae Irvin in 1925
والعلامة الشهيرة التي رُسمت من قبل (راي إيرفين) في عالم 1925
is now in Cyrillic.
الآن تستخدم في الحروف السيريلية
So, what makes me really excited about this moment
لذا ما يجعلني متحمسة جدًا لهذه اللحظة
is the way that ...
هو أن
You know, free press is essential to our democracy.
أن الصحافة الحرّة مهمة لديموقراطيتنا
And we can see from the sublime to the ridiculous
ونستطيع أن نرى من الأفضل إلى الأسوء
that artists can capture what is going on
أن الرسّامين يستطيعون تصوير ما يحدث
in a way that an artist
بشكل ما
armed with just India ink and watercolor
و أدواتهم هي فقط حبر أسود و ألوان مائية
can capture and enter into the cultural dialogue.
ويدخلون بذلك في الحوار الثقافي.
It puts those artists at the center of that culture,
ذلك يضعهم في قلب الحوار الثقافي،
and that's exactly where I think they should be.
وهو بالضبط ما أراه المكان الذي ينبغي أن يكونوا فيه.
Because the main thing we need right now is a good cartoon.
لأن الشيء الرئيس الوحيد الذي نريده الآن هو فيلم كارتون جيد.
Thank you.
أشكركم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)